JASON WESTON: Now, I
don't know about you,
but these days I'm using AI in
my everyday life quite a lot,
like to help me create
art, write code, write
formal letters, ask questions,
brainstorm all kinds of stuff,
and that's only really been
possible very recently.
I think AI research
is we're pretty
privileged to be in this
time in human history,
and see these improvements
happening in real time.
And we've seen how
quickly they evolve,
but I still think
there's a lot left to do.
I think we can expect still
more large improvements even
in the near future
and next few years,
and we've seen that even in
the last months with O1, R1,
and so on.
Big improvements in various
benchmarks in reasoning.
And after all that, it's a
very young field overall,
but like that subfield with
learning chain of thought.
I mean, chain of thought itself
is only really from 2022,
so, yeah, I think
it's really impressive
how fast things are moving.
So in the context
of this talk, I'm
going to be talking
about methods
for self-improving
language models,
and that means getting
better at tasks in particular
that will mean that they're
getting better at reasoning so
that they can better get
better at those tasks.
So for an AI to
train itself, I mean,
that means it needs to do this
introspection as its training,
so normal, classical training
was like this fixed data set
and it would learn
from it, but that's
kind of moving now a little
bit where in like reinforcement
learning setups, and
particularly with reinforcement
learning from AI feedback models
are sort of training themselves
in a much more
sophisticated way.
For example, we
can imagine models
that create new challenges,
tasks to train themselves
on, they can evaluate themselves
whether they're getting them
right, so we call
that self-rewarding,
and then update themselves based
on what they've understood,
so that means then they're going
to be getting more knowledge,
more reasoning ability.
And so a research
question is, can they
do this kind of
training on themselves,
and can that help them
become superhuman?
So I have a picture down here
of one particular approach
for that that's called
self-rewarding language
models, which I'm going to
be talking about a bit later.
But in terms of
reasoning, when we're
doing this kind
of self-improving,
you can look at this as two
different ways of improving
reasoning, so these are
called system 1 and system 2
sometimes by people.
So system 1, like in humans,
we see that as reactive
and relies on associations,
and in machine learning models,
or LLMs it can be
the same thing.
So you can think of
the transformer itself,
the neural network, as this
kind of performing this system 1
reasoning, so where you
have this hidden states
in the neural
network that's going
through a whole bunch
of multiplications,
attentions, and so on, that it
can be seen as your system 1
reasoning.
So in that case, you have
a fixed compute per token,
you're directly
outputting the answer,
but there's some
problems with LLMs
as we have them
now, in particular,
they can learn spurious
unwanted correlations,
there's hallucination,
sycophancy, jailbreaking,
and I'm going to show you
some of those things later.
And then you can try
and fix this stuff
with what's called
system 2, so that's
more deliberate and
effortful thinking,
and the most common way we
think of that system 2 today
is by generating language tokens
that are a chain of thought.
So now, that's not just
the pushing these numbers
through the neural
net, you're actually
looking at the tokens, the
neural net outputs as a thought
stream before the final tokens
that will be the final response.
Now what's powerful
when you do that is
that system 2 chain
of thought reasoning
can actually do a
whole bunch of stuff
like planning,
search, verification,
various kinds of reasoning,
even though it's generating
autoregressively left to right,
it could still potentially do
all that sets of
thoughts, as you'll see,
models like Deep Sea 103 can do.
Yeah, so those are the
two kinds of things
that we can effectively
improve in, try and improve
like the architecture or
the weights of the model,
and improve system
one, or try and improve
how it generates these
chains of thought,
or other ways of doing system
2 before it outputs a response.
I mean, obviously
they're related
because it's the same language
model doing both things.
That's the goal, try and
do this self-learning
to improve these things.
First, I'm going to go through
some history of how we got where
we are today, and then talk
about more recent works
from the last year or so after
I go through this history.
But before we're going to start
pre-2020, so prehistory if you
like, so language modeling
itself that goes way back.
I mean, yeah, Claude Shannon
in 1950s talked about that,
so it's about taking language
and predicting the next token
or the next word at each
step, and obviously,
that's the pre-training
mechanism we use for large
language models, and that's
how they get their name,
where you're just trying to
predict the probability of these
tokens.
We do this now on
these massive corpora
and pick up those
probability distributions.
So, in 2003, there's
one of the first methods
for doing that with a
neural network that's
Ben Duchamp and Vincent,
so they had word
embeddings at the first layer
and then various layers, tanh,
and softmax to get
the final prediction.
And I just put an interesting
quote there in their conclusions
that they say there's probably
a lot more to be done to improve
the model, the architecture,
computational efficiency,
and they'd like to increase
the capacity without increasing
training time because they want
to deal with corpora of hundreds
and millions of words,
so that's kind of where
we got to some years later.
Now, that was 2003.
Most of the 2000s actually, the
research wasn't really focused
on neural networks.
It was focused on
support vector machines,
so these kernel classifiers.
I worked in that area
too, as you can see,
there's a paper from me, and
it was kind of that, well,
held back the LLM story,
at least for a few years.
So here I have a
slide for myself
and Ronald Collobert
from 2008 presented
ICML, where we were trying to
argue that the support vector
machines of the
day that were used
in these Cascades of systems,
parts of speech tagging
and named entity
recognizers and parses,
and it's not a good idea because
we could train the whole thing
end to end with
a neural network,
and no one was really
doing that then.
So we had a paper at that
time, a unified architecture
for NLP, which we considered
a successor to the Bengio work
from 2003 there.
So here what we did was we also
had a neural network with word
embeddings at the first layer,
then convolutional layers a max
over time, which is a
kind of proto attention,
and followed by a softmax.
And we show that you could train
this model as a masked language
model on something like
Wikipedia, which actually
was pretty tricky at the time
with the compute we had, and it
could learn some pretty
interesting things,
like you could see from
the word similarities.
This is obviously
pre word2vec, which
I think was 2013, which
is a simpler model.
This is a more complex neural
net that you could do that,
so you could pre-train
on Wikipedia,
and then afterwards you could
fine tune on tasks of interest
like part of speech tagging,
named entity, chunking, S.R.L,
and that worked.
So yeah, this was a predecessor
to where we are today as well.
It was interesting because at
the time that wasn't appreciated
by everyone in
the NLP community,
so in the Stanford
natural language group,
they had a reading group
there where they called it
a bullshit ICML paper that was
kind of on their public website.
And then this same paper 1 Test
of Time Award at ICML 2018,
and then Stanford
University then
opened the Center for
Research on foundation models
and their position paper
called that same paper
a prescient work, so we kind of
went from bullshit to prescient
in that number of
years, and that's
kind of how the field changed.
Of course, these papers--
I've talked about
just a few papers.
There's many, many papers.
They all build on each other.
I don't like to
think one paper that
was the paper that did something
because they're all this work
builds on top of the
brilliant work before.
But so I just show a few
here of a timeline, though,
of how these things went.
And yeah, the
interesting thing is
of how fast the use of neural
nets in NLP and machine learning
grew from this time,
say, 2008 to 2018.
So there was four
papers in ICML 2008
with the words deep
or neural in them.
And I'm coauthor on two of them.
And then there's
hundreds in ICML 2018.
Obviously, this is a
neural network based
things are the majority today.
That's the paradigm of today.
Of course, can't say what's
going to be in the future,
but it's looking like a
pretty powerful approach.
Yeah.
So, of course, we were
interested in pushing
this further and making
these models reason.
So in 2015 we devised this
set of tasks, very simple task
called baby tasks, which you
ask these simple questions given
little stories.
But the neural nets
of the day LSTMs
actually couldn't solve them.
And so we were hoping
that they could spark
innovation of new methods.
Around the same time the
LLM attention mechanism
was born in 2014.
So [INAUDIBLE] Cho/Bengio paper.
So that was built for
machine translation
where the you'd have a tension
between the target sentence
words and the source
sentence words
so that you could
have an alignment
between the words
in the two languages
so you could translate them.
And you can see this
sort of attention map
picture in the middle
of the slide here.
So yeah, what we showed was that
for these kind of baby reasoning
tasks, if we stack
these layers of tension,
then you could actually do
multiple reasoning steps.
So if you've got a question
like where is John here?
So Daniel went to the bathroom.
Mary traveled to the hallway.
John went to the bedroom.
John traveled to the bathroom.
Mary went to the office.
Where is john?
Then you could attend to
these correct sentences
to get that right.
Actually, that one's pretty
easy because you only
need to attend to John travel to
the bathroom, the last sentence.
That's called one
supporting fact question.
But then you have a two
supporting fact question
where it's a little trickier.
So there, John dropped the milk.
John took the milk there.
Sandra went back
to the bathroom.
John moved to the hallway.
Mary went back to the bedroom.
And the question is,
where is the milk?
So now you have to see
that the model will
attend on the first two layers.
You can see the attention scores
here, and hop 1, hop 2, hop 3.
This is in the story to
two supporting facts.
You see, it attends
to the sentence.
John took the milk there.
And so now it knows
that John has the milk,
and then it can attend
to this next sentence,
John moved to the hallway,
in the further layers
of the neural network so that
it can answer that hallway
is the correct answer.
So this was
basically showing how
in these very simple problems,
the tension mechanism when
stacked layer by
layer can give you
more sophisticated reasoning.
And so this was built
into this neural network
at the time called
a memory network.
So it had these stacked
layers of attention query
and key embeddings,
position embeddings
that it knew which sentence
or token was being attended
to neural networks
between attention layers
and the final softmax layer.
And so in many
ways, it was a kind
of a predecessor to
the transformer, which
improved on this recipe
with some other things
like multi-head
attention, self-attention,
and normalization.
And yeah, that led us
to 2017 with the advent
of the transformer.
And that's more or
less the architecture
we're using today
with some tweaks.
And then Bert in 2018 showed
that a masked language
model with a transformer
could work very well.
And yeah, I just wanted
to link that to a paper
from 2014 with
Sutskever, Vinyals,
and Quoc V. Le which was showing
that you could do sequence
to sequence learning
with neural networks.
And I think that wasn't
with attention maps yet.
But still the conclusions
from that paper
were essentially the
scaling hypothesis
that we're using today.
So you can see this
conclusion slide.
If you have a large
big data set and you
train a very big neural network,
then success is guaranteed.
It's a little bit glib.
But yeah, this scaling
hypothesis, essentially,
when Ilya Sutskever
went to OpenAI,
they drove this hypothesis
making or GPT 1, 2,
3, 4 and so on.
These are bigger
models, more data,
and indeed this has worked.
So these are basically
the ingredients that
have taken us to some degree--
I saw LLMs everywhere,
so I asked actually
an LLM to give me
a list of LLMs that
have come out in year order.
This doesn't
include all of them,
but you can see a bunch
that have come out here.
But that's just
so far been mostly
about language modeling and
the language model objective
function.
And that isn't actually enough.
So we do need other ways
of training these models.
And I would characterize
2020 onwards
as exploring that more deeply.
Now we have these
better language models.
So 2019 actually, we did
a work on dialogue agents,
which we call the self-feeding
chatbot, where they could train
not only just with this
language model objective
but by using a reward model.
So we train a reward
model, and then
during conversations
with humans,
if it thinks there's a large
reward for one of the things it
said, it can add that back
into the training set,
and then do
supervised fine tuning
on this ever-growing data set.
So this was kind of a
pretty simple version
of what's being done
today with HF and RLAIF.
Then in 2020 we released
this BlenderBot model
that was a pre-trained
language model up
to about 10 billion parameters.
And then crucially, we don't
just use the language model
pretraining objective.
We supervise, fine tune
that on dialogue data
which was human annotated.
And then when you
evaluated this with humans,
they actually said
our best models
were about as engaging as the
average human and superior
to another model from Google
called Meena at the time.
But the actual recipes that
we use today, we do use
supervised fine tuning
today, but there's
some more sophisticated
stuff as well.
So in 2022, you had
the InstructGPT paper,
which advocated more
for reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
So what you do there is
you have this SFT stage
where you collect
demonstration data from humans.
That's step one.
But step two, you also
collect comparison data,
so which of these two
responses is better, A or B?
And then get humans
to rank those.
And then you train
a reward model.
So similar to how we
had a reward model
in the self-feeding chatbot.
But then you use reinforcement
learning with that reward model
to then generalize those
comparisons with the reward
model function to new
generations from your policy.
And try and make
your model better
by generating responses
and essentially judging
with this reward model
and fixing itself.
So a more of a step towards
this self-training goal
beyond the language
model training criterion.
And then there's an
alternative to RLHF.
Well, it's a little bit simpler
called direct preference
optimization.
I mentioned because it's
also pretty popular, DPO.
So it says, OK, let's
not use a reward model.
We've got preference data.
We're just going
to directly push
the probability of the chosen
in a preference pair sort of up
and the probability of the
rejecting the preference pair.
So these would be two possible
outputs from the model,
push one up, push
one down so there's
a margin between the two.
And in certain
experiments, the DPO
works quite well
compared to PPO, RLHF.
And then SFT can also work
but generally a little worse,
but it depends on the setting.
And I think in some
cases, you really
do need the full reinforcement
learning because your policy is
going to change.
So the DPO just with a fixed
preference data like that
can't take that into account.
But we'll see ways
of fixing that
by making it iterative as well.
But overall, you choose one of
those methods SFT, RLHF or DPO
and fine tune your language
model with one of them,
and then you get pretty
good instruction following.
So there isn't necessarily
this explicit chain
of thought reasoning
yet, but compared
to the original language models,
you're doing really well.
So, for example, here this is
from the InstructGPT paper.
You've got this prompt.
What's the purpose of this code
GPT 3 without the fine tuning
doesn't do a very good job.
It instructs-- GPT does a much
better job on the right hand
side.
So, obviously, yeah, today
we all know quite a lot
about using these ChatGPT
type models as we're mostly--
yeah, a lot of the population
is using them at this stage.
So OK, that got me up
to basically having
a really good system 1 model.
It takes in this input,
so this instruction.
It directly spits out an output,
but it isn't doing the system 2
reasoning.
So that's the next step.
And yeah, between, say, 2022 and
2023, the approach to doing that
was what I would call
a prompting approach.
And I'm going to talk
about those first,
and then we're going to
look at more modern things
from the last year
or so where we're
going to more train
directly to do this system 2
reasoning instead.
So chain of thought prompting
the initial papers they
did that in a couple of ways.
One was by what's called
few-shot prompting.
You would have say
for some maths task,
you would have
examples of the kind
of chain-of-though reasoning
you would like to see.
Say if you had a no
eight shot examples,
you'd have eight examples
of doing reasoning.
That's shown here with
the-- instead of just saying
the answer is 11 as
in standard prompting,
you would have rather
started with 5 balls.
2 cans of 3 tennis balls
each is 6 tennis balls.
5 plus 6 equals 11.
The answer is 11.
So that's the chain of thought
there that's highlighted.
So you'd have examples
of that in the prompt,
and now you would generate
from the language model.
And it's going to mimic
that few-shot prompting
and use a chain of thought.
And so that was kind of
one of the first approaches
of prompting.
And then in the other paper
here large language models
are zero-shot reasoners.
They showed actually
it can be even simpler.
You could just say, let's think
step by step in the prompt.
And that could still
bring about these steps
or these chains of
thought could happen
that it could generate before
it generates the final response.
And you get really big
improvements on math tasks.
So you could go from say 10%
on GSM 8K up to 40% or 50%.
So yeah, that's
really spurred people
to push the system to
approaches further.
And it's not just math
tasks that that works for.
So you can also look at the
other failures of system
1 of the base language model.
It also has a factuality
and hallucination issues.
So here's an example query,
name some politicians
who were born in New York.
And the third one
it lists here--
this is from ChatGPT--
is Michael Bloomberg
which is incorrect.
So you can try and set up a
system 2 reasoning type chain
of thought to fix this problem.
So it's not a math problem.
So that's a paper we did called
chain of verification where
the idea is you get this
first baseline response.
You can think of that
now as your draft.
So it's not actually
your final response.
It's part of your
chain of thought.
And then given that
draft, the language model
asks itself more questions
to check its own draft.
So it could ask, where
was Hillary Clinton born?
Where was Donald Trump born?
Where is Michael Bloomberg born?
And then answer those
again as single questions.
Now, the answer might be
different than writing out
this whole list from the name,
some politicians question.
Because it's
phrased differently,
you actually get a different
response from the model.
And models tend to
be better actually
at these single question
answer pairs that
are short compared to these
long responses they write.
They're more likely to get
something wrong somewhere
in the long response.
So when you plan
those verifications
of those verification
questions and execute them,
you can actually get the model
to see its own discrepancy.
So now it actually knows
that Michael Bloomberg
was born in Boston,
even though it's
included him in the
list of politicians
who are born in New York.
And now you can make it
cross-check itself and see
that it was wrong, and write
a final verified response
and treat the old
one as a draft.
And now it gets that correct.
So that's a somewhat
different chain
of thought system 2 reasoning
compared to the math problems.
And yeah, in that work we showed
that on various knowledge tasks,
you can get large
performance in precision
like three times as
good with that approach.
So yeah.
And you could think,
oh, that's sort of--
maybe because that paper was
from a little while ago that it
might be fixed today, but
actually, I tried on ChatGPT 4o,
and it's still making
these kind of mistakes.
Like here I did a query list,
30 most famous women in AI,
and it included Yoshua
Bengio in the list
or what prominent
women work at OpenAI
and it said Ilya Sutskever
as a first in the list.
So still something that's
definitely needs to be fixed.
And you can fix it with this
sort of system 2 reasoning.
I think actually
[? O1 ?] does better.
But yeah.
And there's other things you can
do with this system 2 reasoning
as well.
So here's another problem
with language models
that they have what's called
semantic leakage and sycophancy.
So when you do attention
because it's a soft attention,
it's not sharp.
You're assigning probabilities
across the context.
So there'll be all
these non-zero values.
And it means the whole context
can affect the LLM output.
And this can be bad
because, even basically
we see irrelevant
parts which look
sort of superficially correlated
tend to have an effect.
So, for example, a prompt
like, he likes ants.
His favorite food is-- can get
completed by the language model
as ant-covered chocolate, which
isn't particularly desirable.
He likes yellow.
He works as a school bus driver.
That's from Genen, et al in 24.
I see this as a similar
problem, the sycophancy problem.
If you say something
like as an instruction,
I think that the sun is
yellow when viewed from space,
what do you think?
So you prime with
the wrong answer
because actually, that's an
illusion caused by atmosphere.
Then it will actually agree.
The LLM tends to agree with you
and say yes, the sun is actually
yellow when viewed from space.
So I see that as
a similar problem
that basically you've got
that text in the context,
and it tends to attend to
it and get things wrong.
So another example,
if you add some facts
about some city in the
context, like Sunnyvale,
and then you ask for
someone's birthplace,
it's likely to say
Sunnyvale as the answer.
Yeah, I just typed
in this one today.
Did OpenAI have a model called
self-feeding at one time?
And ChatGPT 4o replied, yes,
OpenAI introduced the concept
of self-feeding in the
Self-feeding Chatbot paper,
which that wasn't
actually from OpenAI.
That was from
Facebook AI Research.
So again, you can
still prime these.
This is a current day problem.
So how can you fix that?
With system 2 reasoning.
So there was a paper called
System 2 Attention we did last--
that was end of
2023, I think, where
you do this chain
of thought reasoning
which attempts to rewrite
the original instruction
and remove the bias.
So again, this is
done by prompting.
So essentially, the prompt is to
give the original instruction,
and then ask the language
model, rewrite this instruction.
Remove the irrelevant
parts and the bias.
And then you'll get
a new instruction.
And then you get
the language model
to answer the
rewritten instruction.
So you want to get
rid of this bias.
And then you can
get better results.
You're not biased as
much by this issue.
So, for example, I
think the sun is yellow
when viewed from space.
What do you think?
When you use this
chain-of-thought system 2
attention, to rewrite that,
it would rewrite it as,
I'm curious about the color of
the sun when viewed from space.
Can you provide
information on this topic?
So to remove the yellow which
was biasing the question
to a certain answer.
And yeah, this works also on
math problems if there's say,
there's parts of
the math problem
which are completely irrelevant
they can actually fool a model,
and it will try
and remove those.
So yeah, this is yeah,
just to show you really
that chain of thought
and system 2 reasoning
is not just for math problems.
There's a lot of
things you a model
can think about with
these intermediate tokens
and fix a lot of problems
in all kinds of tasks
that it's trying to solve.
This last one I show it's
the task of evaluation.
So you're given a question
like an instruction
and two possible responses.
You want the model to say
which of the two responses
is better, which is a really
important thing for training
as we show, because
you could basically
use that as a reward model.
And it's also important
for evaluation as well.
But yeah, you can also do
system 2 reasoning there.
So in this paper,
Branch-Solve-Merge,
the way that was done was again
through prompting by asking,
given that instruction to
first ask the language model
to break down its evaluation
into different criteria
such as relevance, clarity,
accuracy, originality.
And it would come up with those
criteria specific to the task
that it's trying to solve.
And then to generate an
evaluation independently
for each of those
different branches.
And then merge them
back together again.
And it was shown that could
give better evaluation results
through the extra thinking time
basically that the language
model has.
So yeah, that was-- there's
many other works as well during
that period.
But I just wanted to give
an overview of a few of them
to show there was a lot of
prompting approaches that
showed that spending
time thinking could
get you better results.
But what we really want to do is
try and train these models end
to end to be able to
be good at reasoning,
not like just prompting.
So that I'd say the next
wave after that is--
and we're in it right now--
is improving this reasoning
through optimization
and so better reasoning
via self-improvement.
And to get there,
I'm going to start
with the self-rewarding
language models
that I was talking about right
at the beginning of the talk.
And so this is a method
where the LLM proves itself
by assigning rewards to its own
outputs and optimizing itself.
So yeah, where the hope is that
this could lead to it becoming
smarter at each iteration.
And yeah, so the
research question
is, can that make it superhuman?
So the standard reinforcement
learning from human feedback,
which I mentioned earlier in the
talk, uses humans in the loop,
first to create the
supervised fine tuning
data, so the instructions
and their responses,
and then to collect
these judgments.
So which of these two
responses is better, A or B?
Now, yeah, that's shown in this
picture that I showed before.
So there's two spots
where there's a human.
And the problem
is language models
are getting better and better.
So it's just getting a
really tricky job for humans
to be as good as we
need for these tasks.
Humans need to read these
responses really carefully
in order to make decisions.
So, for example,
now that our LLMs
are really good at writing
code or no sophisticated math
outputs, even getting
good at like--
I mean, maybe not perfect
yet, but getting good
at legal or medical
outputs, things like this.
The problem is, it's harder
and harder for humans
to be good labelers
for these tasks.
You might need some of
the best mathematicians
and human mathematicians
in the world
to label whether these
responses are correct or not.
And similarly, you need
really good coders.
Or even if you don't
need them today,
you'll certainly
need them tomorrow.
And so the average human that
you pick from the population,
then they're just not
going to be good enough
at these specialized tasks and
be able to annotate this data.
So this is what motivates
trying to get the language
model to try and help itself.
And so that's
basically otherwise
how can we continue improving
a model if it's already
fairly superhuman compared
to the average human
that you could pick?
So there's two observations
that can help us solve this.
Observation 1 is that we know
language models can continue
improving if they're given good
judgments on response quality,
because that's what we're
shown in reinforcement learning
from human feedback or in
something like DPO as well.
So if you have good preferences
of chosen and rejected pairs,
then you can improve the model
by training and pushing up
the probability of the chosens
and down the probability
to reject it.
And the same thing
for a reward model
with reinforcement learning.
And observation 2
is that we actually
have now language models that
can provide good judgments
on model generation.
So I was showing you the
Branch-Solve-Merge approach
just earlier.
So that's an approach
for a language model
basically to give a judgment on
two responses as an instruction
following task.
So this is called LLM-as-a-Judge
typically where for the language
model it's not any different
a task than all the other
instruction following tasks it
has to do like write some code,
or respond to this
particular question.
And in particular
this question we're
asking is, which of these two
responses is better, A or B?
And there's a bunch of work
showing LLM-as-a-Judge is
actually a pretty good method.
So how about combining
these two things together.
So we replace the human
feedback with the LLM feedback.
So the key idea then is to train
this so-called self-rewarding
language model.
It's going to be its own
judge as its training.
So it needs to have this
instruction following capability
for all the kinds of user
instructions we want,
but one of those
user instructions
is actually the evaluation
task that we're interested in.
So it looks like this.
Here is an instruction.
Here is a model of response.
And then the task is
can you assign a score,
say between 0 and 5?
There'd be other
ways of doing that
as well but to this response
and then based on some rubric.
And then you would expect,
say, chain-of-thought reasoning
process and then
a final judgment
of the score of the response.
So if we have these
two things, then we
can make this model train
itself and be self-rewarding.
So we also go through
an iterative process
of data creation and
curation so that we
close this whole training loop
where we train on this new data.
And then the goal
is the model is
going to get better in terms
of both instruction following
and evaluation
ability in each cycle.
And we empirically
showed that was possible.
So this was right at the
beginning of last year.
So that was the picture
that I was showing right
at the beginning of the talk.
So yeah, we did these
experiments on LLAMA-2-70B.
And we used Open Assistant
as a sort of seed,
so that seed instruction data.
And it also has some
seed evaluation data.
So the LLM-as-a-Judge prompts
that we use looks like this.
So that's asking it
to do chain of thought
and then score out of 5
a particular instruction.
And then we're going to go
through this training loop.
So the first part is it's
going to generate new tasks.
So we use something called
self-instruct to do that.
So basically, you start
with your seed instructions,
which are from humans.
And you use few-shot prompting
with a few of those instructions
to ask the language model to
generate a new instruction.
And then you can do this
hundreds or thousands of times
to get a whole new set of tasks.
Then for those tasks you
can generate responses.
So you'll generate multiple
candidate responses
for each prompt or task, so
let's say four in our case.
And then you generate rewards
with the LLM-as-a-Judge prompt
that I just showed to give
you those scores for each
of the four responses.
And from that you can
generate preference pairs.
So you take the highest
scoring of the four responses,
and that would be
the chosen for DPO,
and the lowest scoring
would be the rejected.
You can carry on
training your model now
with this DPO training, and
then repeat the whole cycle.
Now you have a better
model M t plus 1.
You can go back,
generate new prompts
to generate new responses,
generate new rewards, and so on.
And we do this loop three
times in the experiments
in that paper.
And we're going to
evaluate the performance
on two axes, the ability
to follow instructions
and its ability
as a reward model.
There's some benchmarks called
AlpacaEval 2.0 and MT-Bench
at the time that we used and
another test set of prompts.
And we use GPT 4 evaluation
and human evaluation
to check how this model
performed through the three
iterations of self-rewarding.
And you can see that they agree
with each other humans and GPT 4
that we compare it to doing
supervised fine tuning.
On each iteration, the
model is getting better.
So it's getting better
than the SFT baseline.
And yeah, so that's the
power of this self-training.
And we can look at the
win rate on AlpacaEval 2.0
And this paper got quite a
bit of attention at the time
because this win rate for
such a sort of simple model
was quite good.
It started from
this LLAMA-2-70B.
And the win rate went up
from 10% to 15% to 20%
in the three iterations,
which put it almost on par
with a version of GPT 4.
And this was just done
by the first author
is Weijia Yuan, who's
a PhD student at NYU.
So there wasn't like a big
team building this project
but the algorithm
works quite well.
And yeah, so you could look at
what is actually improving at.
And it does improve
on all kinds of skills
but particularly more
things like humanities,
extraction, STEM role
play and writing more
than it improves
at, say, something
like math, code, and reasoning.
And the reason why that would
be is because the LLM-as-a-Judge
might not be as good at
evaluating math, code,
and reasoning, and so it's
harder for it to improve
on those.
This is a breakdown
of these topics.
You can see that the gap
between the iterations
is smaller for things like
math, which is on the far right.
And then you can measure
the ability of this model
as an evaluator.
And one way of measuring that
is by looking at its correlation
with human judgments.
So the pairwise accuracy-- we
had a whole bunch of metrics
for the pairwise accuracy
metric would show it's agreement
with humans on whether
A or B the right way
around or the wrong way around.
And you can see that
it does increase,
not by a massive amount
but it does increase
over the three iterations.
So it is actually getting better
at being a reward model, which
I think is exciting, because
if the model is getting better
at making judgments of
what's right or wrong,
then it's getting better
at rewarding itself
at following instructions.
So there's a virtuous circle
going on there to some extent.
Of course it plateaus
in experiments,
but it still gives it the
capacity to self-train
to get better than the
initial human annotations
that it had at the beginning.
Now, as I said, it
didn't improve as much
on reasoning tasks.
So the next thing we wanted
to ask was how can we
make it improve on those?
And yeah, so in
April of last year,
we did this work called
Iterative Reasoning Preference
Optimization, which you can
see from the picture it's
a similar pipeline,
but now we're
going to generate
chain of thought.
So in the experiment I
just showed you there
were no chain of thoughts.
It was just a system 1 language
model output the answers
for instruction following.
But in this version, we're going
to generate train of thoughts
and then answers.
And we're going to
compute rewards.
And otherwise the
pipeline is the same.
Now the rewards aren't going
to be done by LLM-as-a-Judge
because we don't trust the LLM
on say these math tasks as much.
I mean, I think that's
a subject of research.
Can we get them to improve by
trusting their own judgments.
But in this work we
just said, OK, we've
got a bunch of
math training data
where we know the
right answer so let's
just use that as a reward.
And this is being
commonly called
in the last weeks is like a
verifiable reward for a math
problem.
So what we're going
to do is we're
going to generate
the chain of thought
and then the final answer.
And then we're going to extract
the final answer from the LLM
response, so remove the
chain of thought part.
Just get the final
answer, and then just
do a match with the answer that
we know for the math problem.
So you can do that with
this kind of prompt.
So where you give
the LLM the prompt.
Your task is to answer
the question below.
Give step-by-step reasoning.
And when you're ready, please
use the format, final answer,
colon.
And then you can just simply
do this heuristic extraction
where you search for
final answer, colon.
Grab the text afterwards.
That should be your answer.
And now just do a string match
or some other fairly simple
match with the answer,
the known gold answer.
And that's how you can
build your DPO pairs
and improve your model and
then again iterate round.
And that's the iteration,
again, is important
because now we've
got a better model
answering these math problems.
We're going to generate
new chain of thoughts
with the better model.
Compute the rewards and
go around in a loop.
And we showed on math
problems like GSM8K
that that's working really well.
So yeah you can see these
improvements across iteration 1
to 4 is gaining a little
bit less than 10% there
and also improves on some
multi-choice problems
on ARC challenge and on these
harder math problems as well.
And yeah, we just showed
that the DPO training
is really important.
You can't just use supervised
fine tuning with this training.
You really need the negative
examples to be pushed down.
Otherwise, it doesn't work.
And yeah, so in 2024, September
or so, OpenAI's O1 came out.
Of course, the exact
method is unknown.
They didn't publish a paper
about it, but they did have--
well, they didn't even show
the chain of thoughts either.
From the model
there was a summary
of the chain of thoughts.
I think they still do that.
But it was capable of answering
some quite sophisticated
reasoning and math problems.
And everyone was wondering,
how did they do it?
Did they use some
kind of process reward
model that was evaluating
the in-between steps?
Did they use MCTS or some really
sophisticated search mechanisms
to train with
reinforcement learning?
A lot of ideas were posted on
Twitter of how they do this.
And then DeepSeek R1 came
out just this January.
And Marc Chen from
OpenAI tweeted,
congrats to DeepSeek on
producing O1 level reasoning
model.
Their research
paper demonstrates
they've independently found
some of the core ideas
that we did on our way to O1.
OK, so then that means assuming
that OpenAI used the same stuff
as DeepSeek, we have
a deep seat paper,
so we can look at what they did.
And in some respects
it's quite similar
to the iterative reasoning
preference optimization
that we did earlier in 2024
that I just showed you.
So they have a prompt,
which asks it to think
and then to put the
answer in a box.
You see this answer
here in the prompt.
And then they extract that.
And then they use a rule-based
verification of correctness
with verifiable rewards.
And they apply that in a loop
generating chain of thoughts,
checking just the
correctness of the answer,
and then rewarding
this correctness.
They use a different
optimization technique.
They don't use iterative PPO.
They use GRPO.
But otherwise, this recipe
looks kind of like that.
It's just done
much bigger scale.
So in the experiments
I showed you
we just had one data set GSM8K.
So key here is start from
a really strong big model.
I think it's a 600 and
something parameter model.
671 billion parameter
model DeepSeek 3.
And then you have a large
amount of this reasoning
data with verifiable rewards.
And you train with this RL
generating chain of thoughts
and rewarding the
ones that it gets
right, and basically, exploring
the space of chain of thoughts.
And they observe that
the chain of thoughts
get longer over training as
it finds more sophisticated
reasoning techniques.
And then the final
model does very well
on these code and math problems,
similar to OpenAI's O1 model.
And this actually was a
big, big news outside of AI.
You can see that NVIDIA's these
articles here on Bloomberg.
NVIDIA's DeepSeek
drop has Wall Street
fixated with their stock
plunging and stuff like that.
So it was surprisingly
big splash.
And then you have a couple
of examples here of the chain
of thoughts that it does.
The one on the left
is from their paper.
It's generating this
answer to this question.
And then in the middle of it,
like the chain of thought,
it says, wait, wait,
wait, that's an aha
moment I can flag here.
Let's reevaluate this.
And it starts saying
some other stuff.
So they were just showing how
it learns to rethink and fix
its own mistakes.
And that was all done just
with this training that just
rewarding the final answer.
And it was doing
the rest itself.
And I personally love
the simplicity of it
that we didn't have to do
really complicated things
in the middle.
It's just rewarding the end.
And you can already get
these impressive results.
So the one on the right is
kind of a more funny one.
Ask DeepSeek to select
a random number.
And it outputs this large
amount of chain of thought
where it overthinks itself.
Maybe I should go with something
like 7777, but that's four 7s,
which might be too obvious.
Alternatively, 1,2,3,
too sequential.
Whereby if I close
my eyes and 42,
wait, no, that's from
Hitchhiker's Guide and so on.
So it's pretty amusing
what it ends up doing.
But yeah, almost a little
human in a way, though.
But I don't think
that's actually
the way we really want to
generate random numbers,
obviously.
Yeah.
So from my own team's work
before that came out so 2024,
October, we were looking to
extend our chain of thought
training results from
iterative reasoning preference
optimization.
We show that could work quite
well with math problems,
but we want chain of thought
reasoning for all problems.
Like even if you're,
I don't know,
thinking about how
to write a poem,
you might do a whole bunch of
thinking, write some drafts,
try and understand what
you're going to write about
before you actually write it,
just to pick an example that's
very different to math.
So we try to follow
the same recipe.
So we have a prompt,
a generic prompt,
just to initialize the model.
And we ask it to respond
to whatever generic query,
but do it in a comprehensive
and detailed way
by writing your
internal thoughts.
And then you must include
this draft response
in its evaluation.
And after you write your final
response, have this special tag.
So again, that's so we can
extract the response out
and separate it
from the thoughts.
And this is the same
trick that we did before
and the same trick
that DeepSeek does.
But here we're going to
do it not on math problems
but on all kinds of other
instruction following problems.
But now we won't have a
verifiable reward anymore,
but we still have these
LLM-as-a-Judge that we were
using in self-rewarding.
So we can use that
on the response
to judge whether the
response is good.
But the difference between this
and the original self-rewarding
work is that we have the chain
of thought generation before it.
So we tried this, and actually,
ended up working quite well.
It gave gains on AlpacaEval
and another benchmark
called Arena-Hard.
It's actually third on the
AlpacaEval leaderboard,
I think at the time, and it was
the best 8 billion parameter
model on Arena-Hard.
I think one interesting
thing about the training.
So again we're doing
this iterative training
with PPO is that--
so this is called yeah, thought
preference optimization, TPO.
And we compare it to
the direct baseline
in this graph in the bottom
right, which is basically
no chain of thought.
And you can see in
the first iterations,
TPO actually makes
the model a lot worse.
And that's because
these language models--
so we're using LLAMA
8-bit 8 billion--
they're already
really well fine tuned
to be good without
the chain of thought.
So that had a massive
advantage over trying to make
it do the chain of thought.
But after we train it on
successful chain of thought
outcomes using the
LLM-as-a-Judge or the reward
model, then you can see
that the gap closes,
and then it starts improving
on iteration 3 and 4,
and now it's better than
the direct baseline.
So yeah.
So I think this was
really promising
because it showed you could do
this chain of thought training,
not just for math problems
or verifiable tasks
but for anything.
And yeah, so here's a couple
of examples of things it does.
So you can say for a
query, write me a poem
or what dog breed is smallest?
It's going to do a whole
bunch of thinking, like draft
responses and evaluation or
various thought processes
before it gets the output.
Yeah.
And then DeepSeek
R1 in their paper,
not 100% sure if
it's doing something
the same as what we're
doing there with TPO,
but there's a hint it
is because it says--
here I highlighted
it for general data,
we resort to reward
models to capture
human preferences in complex
and nuanced scenarios.
So I think they're also
generating chain of thought
and then doing that.
But it wasn't fully
spelled out in their paper,
so it wasn't completely clear.
And then there's other
things we can do.
So these, as far
to my knowledge,
aren't actually yet in
these bigger models.
So these are more just
like research papers
that hopefully then get scaled
up to these bigger models.
The next work we did to try to
show that the language model so
far we've shown it's quite good
at improving its instruction
and reasoning
ability, but we also
want to explicitly improve its
ability to evaluate itself.
Because if we can
do that, then when
it's doing these
reward model judgments,
it's going to get
better at everything.
It's going to get better at
structure and following as well.
So this work is called
Meta-Rewarding language models,
where it's going to try to
improve its own judgments
by meta judging its judgments.
So, obviously, a little
bit meta this work.
So yeah, now you can see the
language model in three roles.
As an actor, so
following instructions.
As a judge, judging responses
to those instructions.
And as a meta-judge it's going
to judge its own judgments.
And I'll show you
how you can do that.
We call that LLM
as a Meta-Judge.
So there's a prompt for that.
So you'd have a given
instruction from the user,
a response from, say, a model,
and then judgment A and judgment
B, which could include
the chain of thought
and the final verdict.
And then you want
the language model
to judge which of the
judgments is better,
A or B. Now, we have a
particular algorithm then
for basically taking
all different judgments,
calculating the meta
judgments, and then the Elo
score amongst them.
But the reason to do that is
to create preference pairs
amongst judgments.
So now we can say,
OK, this judgment
looks better than that judgment
because our meta-judge tend
to say that.
And so we can construct
preference pairs again
with DPO of which
judgments are better.
So now we've got two
types of preference pairs,
the ones we had before
which were like response.
Response chosen is better
than response rejected.
But now we also
have judgment chosen
is better than
judgment rejected.
And we train the model
with both types of data.
So this is different
to basically
self-rewarding language models
that I showed earlier only
had the top part
of this picture.
So it didn't really have
an explicit mechanism
to improve its ability
to evaluate things.
And yeah, so this work, I think,
it's exciting because it helps.
We actually get better win rates
on say AlpacaEval with that.
And yeah, this plot
you can see again we
see the improvement
over iterations.
But it's above the performance
of the self-rewarding model that
doesn't have this
meta-judge training.
And even the
self-rewarding model
tends to plateau a bit
here on iteration 4,
whereas it's still going up
for the meta rewarding model.
So I think that's
pretty exciting.
And yeah, I've
got one more thing
to talk about, which is how to
improve the chain of thoughts
for judgments for evaluation.
So that's another recent work
actually only out last week.
So this work is called
Thinking LLM-as-a-Judge.
And the goal is to generate
these long chain of thoughts
similar to R1 but for the
task of judgment of responses.
Again, so that we have good
rewards for training our models.
So here's an example
from the model
we trained of what it can do.
Outputs this evaluation plan
of how it's going to evaluate,
and then executes on the plan
and gives this final verdict.
Yeah.
So we have a training
mechanism for that.
And the trick here is you can
look at the evaluation task
actually as a verifiable task if
you know which of two responses
is better.
So let's say you've
got an instruction.
You've got response
A and response B.
If you know in advance that
A is better or B is better,
then that's like a verifiable
task like the math tasks.
We can compute the
reward directly.
We don't need to say a
language model LLM is a judge
to agree with our output.
So the trick in this
work, the first trick
is to generate synthetic
evaluation data
so that we have a
verifiable task so we
know which one's better.
And once we have
that verifiable task,
we can essentially
do something a bit
like the iterative reasoning
preference optimization, IRPO,
because we can compute the
rewards directly and build
these preference pairs to
improve the chain of thoughts
for evaluation.
There's a couple
of extra details
here where in this
particular case,
we actually asked it to
do a plan first and then
execute on the plan, which
is this 2 is the left hand
part of this figure.
So how do we create
this verifiable data?
So this comes from
a previous paper
that we did called
self-taught evaluators.
What we're going to do
is given a prompt x,
we generate a good response
with a language model
or at least we think
is a good response.
Let's say it's a
reasonable response.
And then we generate a
similar prompt x prime,
which is similar
but different to x.
And then we also use same LLM
to generate a good response
to x prime.
We'll call that y prime.
And now the hope
is that, of course,
because x prime
is different to x,
y prime won't be as
good a response to x.
Right?
So that's the thing that
basically y should be preferred
over y prime for input x.
So this now becomes
our verifiable task
that we're going to
use for training.
So the only question there
that was a bit of an unknown
was how do you make this
similar but different prompts?
And, of course, we use an
LLM to do that as well.
So we say please generate a
modified instruction that's
highly relevant but
not semantically
identical to the
instruction above.
And then this is what gives us
the similar instruction which
we can then generate
the lower quality
response for the original
instruction from.
And yeah, that's roughly the
high level picture of this work.
There's some
ablation studies here
where we showed
that these plans are
superior to not thinking at
all, so no chain of thought.
But in general, it's good to
have the plans as unconstrained
as possible.
Like, if you
encourage them to be,
for example, lists of criteria
or verification questions
which are some other works
have used with prompting,
then the results get worse.
And I think that's in line
with the O1, R1 style results
as well, where
basically you don't
want to constrain too much
the chain of thought thinking
processes of these
language models,
but you want to
train and find out
what it's going to be good at.
And then, yeah, after we train
this model using LLAMA-3.1
or 3.3-70B as a base where
it gets a very good results.
Actually, state of the art
on this benchmark called
RewardBench, which evaluates
reward models for LLM-as-a-Judge
generative models.
And it's also quite good
on some harder evaluation
tasks on some newer benchmarks
that just came out like RM-Bench
and FollowBench Eval.
And yeah, that's really all the
things I'm going to talk about.
I think I talked
about enough already.
So I'm just a little bit of a
summary of these recent works
from the last year.
Self-rewarding
models they're models
that can train
themselves to get better.
And the hope is that could
be a path to superhuman AI
as the model improves itself.
We've seen how
verifiable rewards
can help to train chain of
thought for better reasoning.
So I showed you this
iterative reasoning preference
optimization technique.
But DeepSeek R1 have related
techniques basically all using
these verifiable
rewards on the output,
and then letting
the chain of thought
don't penalize it, just
find ones that work well
during your training cycle.
And then you can also use
these verifiable rewards
to improve the evaluation
ability of the model.
So that's the thinking
LLM-as-a-judge that I just
showed.
And then, of course, if we
have these better judges
with these chain of thought, the
whole thing can go in a cycle.
We can use those to help train
to think on nonverifiable tasks,
because we can use this Thinking
LLM-as-a-Judge to train those
models.
And we call that thinking LLMs,
which I showed earlier as well.
And then, finally, you can use
this meta-rewarding concept
to judge their own judgments
is another way of improving
their evaluation ability.
So I've shown you a
few separate papers.
But the goal of the
bigger model release
is to try and put some
of these ideas together.
So yeah, some of those
more recent things
like meta-rewarding
and thinking LLMs
need to go together with the
earlier ideas all in one system.
And we'll see how
far we can push that.
And, of course, still
looking for new ideas.
And they're going to be coming
in the coming days, weeks,
months, and years, I'm sure.
So yeah, of course, there's
lots of other directions.
And just to throw one out
there is all the reasoning
that I've been talking
about was with chain
of thoughts that were text.
It's generating text
from the language model.
Now, you don't have
to do that right.
You could the transformer
itself does reasoning
by all these multiplications
inside the neural net.
It's all manipulating
vectors in the hidden
states of the network.
And so why does this system 2
reasoning have to be tokens?
Maybe that could also be this
continuous vectors as well.
So we explored that in
a recent paper method
called COCONUT, where we
replace the chain of thought
of outputting tokens with
outputting vectors instead.
And we showed that has
some promise, actually.
It could at least match the
performance on some tasks
and even outperform classical
chain of thought on some more
difficult search tasks.
But these are all quite
small scale tasks,
so it remains to be seen how far
people can push that direction.
I think there's
some reasons to want
to have the chain of
thought in human language,
natural language.
I think it's a nice thing for
safety and interpretability.
But, as I said, the
neural network itself
isn't interpretable in
that way, the internals
of the transformer.
So there's something we
have to work out, I think.
And I got another slide
about what else comes next.
I think there's so much more
exciting research to be done.
So Ilya Sutskever
in his "Seq2Seq"
paper Test of Time Award that
was this last NeurIPS talk he
presented some things.
This is a picture of
what he was saying.
What comes next?
He was mentioning agents,
synthetic data, inference time
compute, reasoning,
understanding,
and being self-aware,
which all makes sense.
I think these are all
things that people
are working on today.
Well, maybe the self-aware
one is a little more fuzzy,
but the other ones at least.
And yeah, I would just add
some more detail there.
I think self-improving,
self-evaluation
is really important because
that bottlenecks performance.
So using more of this inference
time compute for evaluation
is only going to help
self improve the model.
And I think that's
sort of related
to this self-aware
comment that he
makes here that a
self-aware model might
be more able to
understand what it knows
and what it doesn't know,
which is evaluation.
And then learning
from interaction.
I think learning how to
reason by actually interacting
with people in the world,
internet, or itself,
are important things.
And so that's related
to the agents point
and the synthetic data
point he makes there.
And then, of course,
it's not just
about improving the
system 2 reasoning.
I think if we can improve
system 1 reasoning,
so like the transformer
architecture
itself, then that's great too.
So maybe there's a better
attention model, some sort of--
or maybe something new.
A neural network layer
we haven't come up
with yet that could change the
scaling laws and the performance
of these models.
And that's great too.
So yeah, plenty to do.
And it's going to be
exciting to see what happens.
Thank you.